<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Discourse of toleration with some observations upon the late act of Parliament.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36107</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1610</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15512</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12006057</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12006057</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52329</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36107)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52329)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 866:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Discourse of toleration with some observations upon the late act of Parliament.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bristol Public Library, Bristol, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52329:1"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE OF TOLERATION: With ſome OBSERVATIONS UPON The late Act OF PARLIAMENT.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1691.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="note">
            <pb facs="tcp:52329:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:52329:2"/>
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>IT will appear upon the peruſal of the following Diſcourſe, that the Author of it, attending only to what he conceived to be the Senſe of the Act for Toleration, and not having recourſe to the exact Words thereof, has a little miſtaken that Statute. For he ſays, That <hi>all thoſe are excluded from the benefit of this To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration, who do not believe the Doctrine of the</hi> Trinity, <hi>as it is believed and taught in the Church of</hi> England.</p>
            <p>Now the Clauſes in the Act concerning this matter, are in <hi>Page 309,</hi> and <hi>Page 317.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the former, 'tis provided that <hi>Perſons in Holy Orders, or pretending to Holy Orders, Preachers, or Teachers in Diſſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Congregations, ſhall be free from the Penalties of the Act for reſtraining Non-conformiſts from inhabiting in Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, and of the Act of Uniformity; Upon</hi> condition only of <hi>their taking the Oaths, and declaring their approbation of and ſubſcribing to the Articles of Religion mentioned in a Statute made 13th</hi> Eliz. (viz. the <hi>39</hi> Articles,) <hi>except the 34th, 35th, and 36th, and ſome words of the 20th.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the other Clauſe, 'tis enacled that <hi>the benefit of the Act ſhall not extend to any Perſon that ſhall deny, in his Preaching or Writing, the Doctrine of the Bleſſed Trinity, as it is declared in the aforeſaid Articles of Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that none but publick Preachers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are comprehended in theſe Reſtrictions. All that are not ſo, may believe what they pleaſe concerning the <hi>Trinity,</hi> without being excluded from the benefit of this Act. And ſo indeed may Preachers too: Only they muſt not teach publickly any thing contrary to thoſe Articles, which they are to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe, and declare their Approbation (not Belief) of.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:52329:3"/>
            <p>A learned Prelate of our Church, (Dr. <hi>Jer. Taylor,</hi>) in excuſe for the many Divines of our Church, (who tho' they incline to the <hi>Arminian</hi> Opinions, touching Free Will and Predeſtination, yet ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to the <hi>39</hi> Articles, which manifeſtly favour the contrary Doctrine, <hi>viz.</hi> that of <hi>Calvin,</hi> which is embraced by moſt ſorts of Diſſenters) in ſome of his Writings, tells us, That <hi>thoſe Articles were never deſigned as Declarations of Truths neceſſary to be believed; but as Articles only of Peace; which no Subſcriber ſhould oppoſe or preach againſt.</hi> And that this is not only the Senſe of one Doctor, but indeed the general Senſe of all the Church of <hi>England,</hi> eſpecially in the matter of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> appears by her admitting, us to both the Sacraments, without requiring any Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Belief in that point, ſo as it is explained in the <hi>Creed</hi> called <hi>Athanaſius</hi>'s, or in the <hi>39 Articles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now juſt what thoſe <hi>Articles</hi> are by this Doctor lookt upon to be, in reſpect to the Clergy of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> ſuch by this Act are they (and particularly the Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> as it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd in them) made to the Diſſenting Miniſters; Articles, I mean of Peace, and no more.</p>
            <p>Thus it appears indeed that the Act does not (as this Writer ſays) <hi>exclude all Perſons from the benefit of this Toleration who believe not the</hi> Trinity, <hi>as 'tis taught in the Church of</hi> England. But nevertheleſs it muſt be confeſt that all his Reaſonings hold good againſt the Act, upon account of the reſtraint it lies upon Miniſters in their preaching.</p>
            <p>For if in a ſpeculative point, where all Parties pretend to have Scripture, Authority, and Reaſon on their ſide, the Teachers of all Perſwaſions are obliged to ſubſcribe to the Deciſions and Explications of one only Party, and not to teach or preach (tho' both themſelves and their Congregations may believe) things contrary thereunto; there ſeems ſtill ſufficient reaſon for this Writers Aſſertion, That <hi>this Act of Toleration is not comprenenſive enough;</hi> And that it not being built upon the true Principle, (<hi>viz. That Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is a Natural Right,</hi> and that therefore Conſcience ought not in any wiſe to be forced) <hi>its Foundation is too narrow to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port it, and it cannot laſt long.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:52329:3"/>
            <head>A Diſcourſe of <hi>Toleration,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THE Goſpel was at firſt planted and propagated by mild and gentle Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods. Our Saviour did not ſend out his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples arm'd with Swords or Spears, or any other Inſtruments of War. Their Weapons were wholly Spiritual: Charity and Humility, Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Condeſcention, were the Arms which the firſt Preachers of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity made uſe of to conquer the World, and bring it into Subjection to Chriſt. By theſe means was the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion ſpread over the World: And it overcame all Oppoſition, by the irreſiſtable force of Truth only. And though the forward Zeal of after-Ages has prompted them to call in the Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign aſſiſtance of Force and Power, yet Experience ſhows, That their En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours have very rarely been Crown'd with Succeſs; which we need not wonder at, becauſe it is very Natural that Religion ſhould be preſerved by the ſame means by which it was at firſt produc'd.</p>
            <p>For my part, I am ſo far from en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vying the Diſſenters the Liberty they now enjoy, or being angry with the Parliament for paſſing the late Act in their Favour, that I think they have done us of the Church of <hi>England</hi> a Kindneſs in it, as well as the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Since now we no longer lie un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der any Obligation of troubling or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieting our Neighbours for Matters of Religion. This Act cannot but calm all Minds that are truly diſpos'd to Peace, and ſtill thoſe peeviſh Animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities which were occaſion'd by the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages of ſome few weak, or paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, or intereſſed men, whoſe over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haſty Zeal carried them beyond the true Rules of Conduct. We all now know who it was ſet thoſe weak men a-work, and made Tools of them, to do a buſineſs which they they never dream'd of. But now they have ſeen their Error, and repented. And we hope, that the good Nature of the Diſſenters will not Father a perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Spirit upon our whole Church, by reaſon of the Miſtakes of ſome few un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinking men in it.</p>
            <p>But methinks I could have wiſh'd that the Act had been more Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive. For I fear, that it being built upon too narrow a Foundation, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not laſt long: Since by this Act ſeveral Perſons are ſtill liable to the Laſh of the Law, upon the account of their bare Opinion in matters of Religion. For upon the ſame grounds that theſe are excepted, ſucceeding Parliaments may think fit to except others whom they judge to hold Opinions equally falſe and dangerous, and ſo more and more by degrees, till at length the whole <hi>Toleration</hi> dwindles into nothing. For if it be once allow'd, That ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons may juſtly be puniſhed for Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes in Judgment, in ſuch things as have no relation to Civil Affairs, it will be very difficult to aſſign any good Reaſon why others ſhould be wholly exempted from the Penalties of the Law, and not be puniſhed for hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing falſe Opinions, provided the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment ſhall at any time ſo think fit.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:52329:4"/>
            <p>It ſeems a ſtrange Paradox, that men ſhould contend for Liberty of Conſcience, as a Natural Right, and yet not be willing to allow all men this Priviledge; as if Nature were ſo far a Step-Dame to ſome of her Children, as to deny them a Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to the Common Rights of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſs, That ever ſince I came to conſider things, I have been of Opinion, That <hi>Conſcience ought not to be forc'd;</hi> and that no man was juſtly puniſhable for differing in his Judgment (in any Point whatever) from the Eſtabliſhed Religion. For the Confirmation of which Opinion, I humbly propoſe theſe following Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is not in our own power to believe as we pleaſe. If upon mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken Grounds, I believe that to be true, which is really falſe; yet ſtill I ſo believe, and cannot but believe, till I am convinc'd of my Error. But after a clear and full Conviction, I throw aſide my former Opinion, and cannot poſſibly (though I would) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it. For as <hi>Plato</hi> well obſerves, <hi>Every Soul is unwillingly deprived of Truth.</hi> And 'tis beyond the power of a Man to reſiſt Truth, when it once plainly ſhews its ſelf unto him.</p>
            <p>Since therefore our Errors are not voluntary, we ought not to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd for them. For what we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not help, is at leaſt excuſable, if not juſtifiable. And all Error intrudes it ſelf againſt a Man's Will; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is not puniſhable. For 'tis unjuſt to puniſh where there is no Fault; and it is to Fault for a man not to do what it is impoſſible for him to do.</p>
            <p>Nor doth Force make any Altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Caſe. It may indeed make us diſſemble, and play the Hypocrites, and cauſe us to profeſs that we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve what we really do not believe: But it cannot change our Minds. For we ſhall ſtill (ſo long as our Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is not convinc'd) retain the ſame Sentiments we had before. Therefore Men ſhould be reaſon'd, and not forc'd into a right Faith.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Though an Erroneous Faith be ſuppoſed to be never ſo dangerous and deſtructive to the Soul that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertains it, yet it injures no body but him that has it. If my Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour embraces Heretical Opinions, the hurt is only to himſelf. It nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hinders my Salvation, nor is it any prejudice to my Temporal Affairs. Indeed, if falſe Opinions did any way violate the Rights of others, then there might be ſome Colour for proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting the Authors of them; even tho they could not help what they did, and ſo conſequently were guilty of no Crime. For Self-preſervation is an unalterable Law of Nature, which warrants every one to defend his own Right. Thus we commonly deſtroy Vermine, Birds and Beaſts of Prey, becauſe they injure us; though we know (at the ſame time) that they only act according to their Natures, and are not Criminal in ſo doing.</p>
            <p>But here ſome may urge, That dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in Opinions gives birth to Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and Sedition, and often ends in Rebellion; it fills all places with Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order and Confuſion, and is inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with the Quiet and Happineſs of Society.</p>
            <p>Now if it could be prov'd, That ſuch diſmal Conſequences would na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally and neceſſarily flow from a Toleration, then I confeſs, That every man that lov'd his Countrey, ought to oppoſe it. It would be a great happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, if Mankind were united in one Faith, and we all thought and ſpake the ſame things: But this is a bleſſing rather to be wiſh'd than hoped for. Mens apprehenſions of things being ſo
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:52329:4"/>various, it is morally impoſſible, that we ſhould not differ in Opinion.</p>
            <p>But however, Force is not the beſt, nor only, way of preſerving Peace. For if men would but be prevailed upon to lay aſide prejudice and paſſion, and bear with one another; if they would be ſo rational, as not to ſuffer their Love and Kindneſs to be leſſen'd by a difference in Opinion; if every one had Liberty to enjoy his own Opinion, and thought it his duty to permit o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to do the like; we ſhould never have any the leaſt occaſion to quarrel or contend about Religion. If this mild and peaceable Doctrine were once heartily embrac'd, and generally enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd, it would ſoon ſtifle all Heats and Animoſities, and reſtore that Love and Charity, which by the Goſpel we are obliged to practice, even towards our Enemies and Perſecutors, much more towards our Friends and Brethren, though in ſome Points their Opinions are different from ours. And then, though we were not united in Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet if we were in Love, that very Love would compoſe our differences, and ſettle a firm and undiſturb'd Peace among us.</p>
            <p>And that this is not a meer Notional <hi>Chimaera,</hi> which has been entertained only by ſome few Bookiſh men, who were never verſed in the World, and ſo underſtand little or nothing of the Temper and Inclinations of Mankind; but that it is a thing really practicable, is evident from the Experience of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 4000 years; during which time, the <hi>Heathen</hi> World, though divided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to as many Opinions as we now are (and ſome of them about matters of the higheſt Conſequence in Religion) did nevertheleſs enjoy a conſtant and unin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted Peace, being never troubled with any Wars, Feuds or Diſturbances, upon the account of their differences in Religion.</p>
            <p>If it be aſſerted, That later Ages have afforded Inſtances of a quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Nature, and that our Diſputes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Religion, have not only baniſh'd all Love and Kindneſs from among us, but have oftentimes involved us in Blood: I anſwer, That 'tis not the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in Opinions, but the refuſing to give Liberty to thoſe who diſſent from us, that has been the chief occaſion of thoſe Miſeries and Calamities that have befallen us. Oppreſſion unites the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Sects, and cauſes them to joyn as one, that they may regain their loſt Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty. This occaſions a continual ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gling betwixt them and the Eſtabliſh'd Church. And from hence all the Wars and Buſtles that have happen'd in the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> World, upon the account of <hi>Religion,</hi> have had their Riſe. If therefore a full and impartial Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion were once ſettled, all occaſion of difference would immediately ceaſe; and the Diſſenters having no juſt cauſe of Diſcontent, would be no longer dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Subjects. But if any prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Party, moved by Ambition, and encourag'd by the conſidence of their great Numbers, ſhould attempt any thing againſt the Goverment, 'tis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable that many ſober and peaceable Men even of their own Party would oppoſe them; ſince they would now want the moſt plauſible pretence of drawing them in. But, to be ſure, Intereſt would oblige all other Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to ſtand by the Government, and to guard and ſupport it; becauſe they know that under it they ſhall enjoy the freedom of their Religion, and that they need not fear the ſeverity of the Laws, ſo long as they neither injure their Neighbours, nor offend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Civil Peace. Hence it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears that it is the intereſt of Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors to indulge Diſſenters, ſince that will make them to ſit more ſafe and ſecure.</p>
            <p>A Toleration likewiſe would very much conduce to the preſervation of the eſtabliſhed Church. For this would cauſe the ſeveral Sects to watch and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:52329:5"/>have an Eye upon one another. Every Party would fear another's being upper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt. Becauſe if that ſhould ever hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, they could not eaſily hope for ſo kind and charitable dealing, as they had formerly receiv'd from thoſe they had diſpoſſeſs'd, who had given them Liberty.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Tho' ſome Men pretend that it is out of Charity to their Souls, that they force Diſſenters into the Church, Jeſt by dying in an erroneous Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they ſhould periſh eternally, yet is this pretence vain and groundleſs. For we all know that it is not the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king profeſſion of the true Religion, nor the outward Conformity to its worſhip, that will ſave us. 'Tis the Mind that God chiefly regards; and what ever we do, if we do it not in the ſincerity of our Heart, it is nothing worth.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Truth oftentimes lies ſo much in the dark, that it is very difficult to find it out; And Error carries oftentimes along with it ſuch a fair appearance of Truth, that it doth not only im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon the weak and careleſs, but does alſo ſometimes deceive the wiſe and diligent Enquirer. Since then there is ſo great hazard of our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing betrayed into Errors, (and that upon probable grounds,) methinks good nature ſhould encline us to make poor miſtaken Souls, objects of our pity rather than anger.</p>
            <p>Beſides, ſince no Perſon is ever the more infallible for being inveſted in the Supreme Power, it is not impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible but that the Rulers and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates themſelves (not being able to ſee through the thick Miſts where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with Truth is veiled) may inſtead of their ſuppoſed <hi>Jum</hi> embrace a Cloud; And the ſeeming Truth they ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly contend for, may poſſibly be Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror hid under a fair diſguiſe. This, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks, ſhould cauſe Magiſtrates to be very cautious how they puniſh Men for their opinion in Religion; leſt while they fancy themſelves to be rooting out Error, they ſhould indeed oppoſe the Truth. This we know was St <hi>Paul</hi>'s own Caſe, who out of his great zeal to the glory of God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted the true Religion, and cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly murthered the beſt and moſt faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of the Servants of God. And if we examine the Opinions of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Rulers of the World, we ſhall find amongſt them more Patrons of Error, than Defenders of the true Faith; which may convince us of the Reaſonableneſs of our Saviours Rule, <hi>viz.</hi> To let the Tares grow until the Harveſt, leſt we root up alſo the Wheat with them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly.</hi> We are not only by Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture enjoyned to try all things, but our Church likewiſe encourages us to examine things our ſelves, and to make uſe of our own judgments in the choice of our Religion. Now it ſeems a little hard to put us upon ſearching and judging for our ſelves, and yet to force us to comply with the former determinations of other Men. This were to puniſh us for fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing that Rule, which ſhe her ſelf hath recommended to us.</p>
            <p>Having thus laid down ſome of thoſe Reaſons which induced me to adhere to the Opinion above-menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, I ſhall proceed to the Excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the Act; and conſider what there is in the Opinions, there men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, that renders thoſe that hold them unfit to be tolerated. And,</p>
            <p n="1">1. All thoſe are excluded from the benefit of this Toleration who do not believe the Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> as it is believed and taught in the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Concerning which, I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that this Doctrine has no rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at all to Civil Affairs. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all who are puniſhed for their miſtakes in this point, are puniſh'd for their bare Opinion only in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: and for an Opinion which is not in the leaſt prejudicial to the State;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:52329:5"/>And therefore they may properly be ſaid to ſuffer for Conſcience ſake.</p>
            <p>It cannot be proved that That Arch-Heretick <hi>Socinius</hi> himſelf, or any of his followers, ever endanger'd the publick Peace, or were worſe Subjects than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men. And conſequently they may as ſafely be permitted to enjoy the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of their Religion as any other Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters whatſoever.</p>
            <p>Beſides, if we ſeriouſly conſider this Doctrine, we ſhall find it clog'd with ſo many and ſo great difficulties, that an honeſt and ſincere Soul may eaſily be miſtaken. If we examine the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture proofs, we ſhall find no clear and expreſs Declaration, that there is a <hi>Trinity</hi> of Perſons in one and the ſame Divine, Eſſence, in all that Sacred Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume: but that it is proved by Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences and Deductions, and thoſe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes ſo far fetch'd, that they may poſſibly be overſeen by a diligent ſearcher. And on the other hand, <hi>John</hi> 14.28. and ſome other places, ſeem ſo favourable to the <hi>Socinian</hi> Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheſis, that if there were no other places of Scripture relating to thoſe points beſides thoſe, we ſhould be apt to interpret them in the ſame ſenſe as our Adverſaries do. And tho' in this Controverſie we multiply Scripture quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, yet ſo many of them are by the moſt learned Men of our own ſide, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed to be unconcluding, that perhaps ſome may from thence be encouraged to ſuſpect the reſt.</p>
            <p>If from Scripture we paſs to Reaſon, that rather diſcourages, than any ways ſupports or defends the Orthodox Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. The Arguments which are urg'd from thence are confeſſed to be ſuch as we can give no clear ſolution to. And it is no wonder that our weak underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings are puzzelled in the Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſo ſublime a Myſtery. Nor is it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſparagement to our Cauſe that we refuſe to make Reaſon a Judge in a Caſe ſhe has ſo very little knowledge of. 'Tis not a ſufficient Argument to overthrow our Doctrine, that we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſolve all the difficulties that are ſtarted about a matter which is of ſo high a nature, that it is above humane underſtanding. We confeſs it to be too great for us to fathom. For it would be raſhneſs and inadvertency, if not madneſs, for a finite Being to propoſe to it ſelf the Comprehenſion of Infinity. But as for the <hi>Socinians</hi> (who believe the Objections to be ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly unanſwerable, and think that it may be proved that the Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity</hi> implies a Contradiction,) They lie under a ſtrong temptation of being of an Opiinon contrary to us, and to interpret ſuch places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as relate to this Doctrine in a different ſenſe from what we uſually give of them. For it is a Maxim ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally allowed by Proteſtants, that what can be clearly proved to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Reaſon is impoſſible to be true; and therefore ought upon no account whatever to be received. And tho' we know that no ſuch thing can be proved of the Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> yet there are ſuch ſeeming appearances, as may probably miſguide an honeſt and well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaning Man.</p>
            <p>If we are willing to be guided by the Authority of the Fathers, we ſhall find that thoſe who are moſt ancient, and lived in the firſt Ages of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, are claim'd both by the <hi>Socinians</hi> and us, and both ſides equally pretend to quote them as Favourers of the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion which each Party holds. And the truth is, they have deliver'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in ſuch ambiguous and obſcure Terms about this queſtion, that 'tis a hard matter to un-riddle what their true Sentiments were concerning it. For they (as St. <hi>Jerom</hi> obſerves, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pol.</hi> 2. <hi>Adv. Ruff.</hi> p. 223.) before the <hi>Southern</hi> Devil <hi>Arrius</hi> aroſe at <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria, innocenter quaedam, &amp; minùs cautè locuti ſunt.</hi> And therefore a very lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Man, who is at preſent in an emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent ſtation in our Church, might upon
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:52329:6"/>good grounds juſtifie what he has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in private, that this is the hardeſt Controverſie we have to manage.</p>
            <p>The Conſideration of which ſhould, methinks, be ſufficient to beſpeak the Candor of all charitable perſons, in the behalf of thoſe unfortunate Souls, who are unwillingly involv'd in this Error, ſince they have ſuch difficulties to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter with, as are almoſt inſuperable.</p>
            <p>Such Thoughts as theſe might prevail with <hi>Salvian</hi> to entertain ſo favourable an Opinion of the <hi>Arrians,</hi> that though he ſufficiently diſlik'd their Hereſie, yet becauſe they firmly believ'd themſelves to be in the right, he refuſed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn rhem; and conceived more hopes of ſuch mens Salvation, than of the moſt <hi>Orthodox Chriſtians,</hi> who lead ill Lives; and he gives his Opinion of them in theſe mild Terms, <hi>How they ſhall be puniſhed for it, in the Day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, none can know but the Judge.</hi> Nay, a very Learned Man of our Church, (Dr. <hi>Crakenthorp</hi>) goes further, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes all ſuch from Herefie, who profeſs <hi>Arrianiſm</hi> in the ſimplicity and ſincerity of their hearts, and are willing to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake it, upon manifeſtation that the Scriptures teach the contrary; and he compares their Caſe to St. <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s profeſſing <hi>Re-baptization,</hi> and <hi>Irenaeus</hi> the <hi>Millenary Hereſie,</hi> p. 109. <hi>Vigilius dormitans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> urges this Principle higher ſtill; for thus he argues: <hi>Sure he that makes right Reaſon the Judge of his very Principles, muſt needs be ſo rational and ingenuous, that he can never be an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick, though he ſay the very things that Hereticks do.</hi> (Infallibility of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> p. 51.)</p>
            <p>If it be objected to the <hi>Socinians,</hi> That they are <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> and deny the True God; and Idolaters, in worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping a Creature inſtead of God, I reply:</p>
            <p>The Charge of <hi>Atheiſm</hi> is ſo ill-ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and extravagant, that it needs no Anſwer. For how is it poſſible, that they ſhould deny the True God, who own the ſame God that the Scriptures declare unto us, and whom all <hi>Chriſtians</hi> adore? The difference between the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinian</hi> and the <hi>Orthodox,</hi> is not about, which is the True God (for they both worſhip the ſame), but about the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of his Subſiſtence, <hi>whether this God doth ſubſiſt in but One Perſon, or in Three?</hi> Now if every Miſtake about the Nature of God, be a Denial of him, I fear there are but few who confeſs the True God. But if not, then we may allow the <hi>Socinians</hi> to hold the True God, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they acknowledge him to be God, who is <hi>Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt;</hi> tho they differ about the Mode of his Being, and deny that he is <hi>Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it be urg'd, That this is no ſlight and trivial Error, but of pernicious conſequence, highly derogating from the Honour of the Second and Third Perſon; I anſwer, That ſeveral other Diſſenters profeſs Opinions as blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous as this, and as diſhonourable to the whole Godhead, as this is to the Two Laſt Perſons; and yet theſe are tolerated. As for Inſtance; The Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Abſolute Reprobation,</hi> is utterly inconſiſtent with the Wiſdom and Goodneſs of God. Now certainly they who rob the Deity of theſe Two Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Attributes, make a more diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous Repreſentation of him to Mankind, than either the <hi>Arrians</hi> or <hi>Socinians</hi> do. If it be alledged in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of theſe Perſons, That it was their great Zeal for the Glory of God, and their deſire to extol his Power, as abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Sovereign of Mankind, that firſt drew them into this Error; Why then may not thoſe who deny the Trinity, make uſe of the like plea? For 'tis well known, that this Hereſie firſt ſprung from the great Antipathy which ſome men bore to the <hi>Heathen</hi> Idolatry, who for fear they ſhould admit of a Rival into God's Throne, as a Partner with him in his Divine Empire, unhappily denied the Trinity.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:52329:6"/>
            <p>To the charge of Idolatry I ſhall op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe nothing: (for I do not pretend to be the <hi>Socinians</hi> Advocate) But if from thence it be inferr'd, That they ought not to be Tolerated, I deny the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence. For if we once grant, That the Magiſtrate may force men from a falſe Religion, by the Penalties of the Law, we ſhall never know where to ſtop; becauſe the ſame Reaſons which juſtifie the rooting out of Idolatry, will ſoon be made uſe of for the ſuppreſſing all ſuch Errors as ſhall be judged hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and dangerous to mens Souls, till at length all men ſhall be forc'd to conform to that Rule of Faith which the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Magiſtrate eſteems to be the only true one.</p>
            <p>Beſides, That power which we allow the Supream Magiſtrate to pull down and deſtroy an Idolatrous Church, may in another time and place be made uſe of to the ſubverſion of the true one. As for Example, in the Caſe before us: We are as much Idolaters in the Opinion of the <hi>Socinians,</hi> as they are in ours; and conſequently where the power is in their hands, they will be as much obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to deſtroy us, as we ure bound, now the Magiſtrate is on our ſide, to root out them. For every one ſuppoſes himſelf to be in the right. So that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of the Legacy of Peace which our Saviour left to his Diſciples, if we give way to theſe perſecuting Principles, we ſhall intail upon the World a perpetual War. And thoſe barbarous and inhu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mane Tortures, for the Exerciſe of which we have a juſt Averſion to the <hi>French</hi> King, will in time gain ſa gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral approbation, and be univerſally pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis'd.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe, for Argument's ſake, that theſe Hereticks, upon the account of the greatneſs of their Error deſerve to be excluded from all Favour, yet is the Exception in the Act 100 large; ſince it ſhuts ſome from the benefit of the Act, whom it expreſly names, as perſons ſit to be Tolerated, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Quakers.</hi> For it appears from their Writings, as well as private Diſcourſes, That many, if not moſt of them, are Heterodox, as to this Point of the Trinity, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently cannot, with a ſafe Conſcience, ſubſcribe the Teſt required of them; which perhaps may cauſe ſome of them to look upon this Act as a Mockery of them, and an Abuſe; ſince (though all the Acts againſt them are actually re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal'd, yet) if they ſhould be Indicted upon any of theſe Statutes, they have no right to this Plea, unleſs they firſt ſubſcribe a Declaration, which they in their Conſciences judge to be falſe.</p>
            <p>The Followers of <hi>Origen</hi> are likewiſe uncapable of receiving any benefit from this Act. For though <hi>Origen</hi> held every One of the Three <hi>Hypoſtaſes</hi> to be truly and properly God, yet his Opinion is ſomething different from what is at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent profeſs'd by the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> Now if any one who delighted in the Writings of this Pious and Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Father, ſhould by degrees be drawn in, to approve of the <hi>Origenian Hypotheſis</hi> concerning this Point, ſurely ſo ſmall an Error in ſuch a nice queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on would not render him unworthy of that Kindneſs which we willingly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow on thoſe who openly maintain Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents of a far more miſchievous Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>I might likewiſe inſtance in ſuch as adhere to the Opinions of the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Church, ſince our Divines are generally very favourable to theſe. Dr. <hi>Stilling fleet</hi> (now Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter</hi>) in his Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of his Anſwer to the King's Papers, pleads in their behalf, <hi>p.</hi> 23. <hi>Is it not</hi> (ſays he) <hi>a very hard caſe, theſe ſhould be excluded the Catholick Church, and conſequently from Salvation, for not rightly underſtanding the ſubtilties of the diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on betwixt Nature and Perſon; as whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Subſiſtence can be ſeparated from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividual Nature; or whether an Hypoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion doth imply that the indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual Nature doth loſe its own Subſiſtence. I appeal to the Conſcience of any good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:52329:7"/>whether he thinks that Chriſt and his Apoſtles did ever make the knowledge of theſe things neceſſary to Salvation, which the ſubtilleſt of their School-men are never able to explain to the Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities of the far greateſt part of mankind.</hi> Now if any of this Opinion amongſt us ſhould urge this Argument for a Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, I cannot think it would loſe much of its ſtrength.</p>
            <p>Add to this, that it looks a little ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere, when we have given ſo general a Liberty, to tie Men up ſo ſtrictly in the moſt nice and difficult point; concerning which Dr <hi>Falkn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r</hi> owns that the <hi>Athanaſian Creed gives ſome explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which are not ſo neceſſary to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood and believed by the meaneſt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities.</hi> Lib. Ecc. c. 4. §. 4. p. 146.</p>
            <p>Moreover, by this Act moſt of the Diſſenters are obliged to ſubſcribe to they know not what. For to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand throughly the Doctrine of our Church in this point, they muſt be ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed not only in our Articles, Common-Prayer Book, and Book of Homilies, but even in the firſt four General Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils; ſince we profeſs to believe what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they have determin'd. And Ibelieve there are but few (even of their Teachers) will pretend to be mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acquainted with them.</p>
            <p>As for the Papiſts, though they are not included in this Toleration, yet I cannot plead ſo much on their behalf, becauſe both their Doctrines and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices are prejudicial to the publick Peace. However, I cannot but wiſh that we had rather excluded them the benefit of the Toleration upon the account of ſuch of their Principles as undermine the very Foundation of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, (ſuch as theſe, That the Pope has power to depoſe Heretical Kings, or that Faith is not to be kept with Hereticks) Then upon account of their believing Tranſubſtantiation; which is a meer religious Doctrine, and the believing of which one way or the other, injures no Man's private Right, nor any ways diſturbs the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Peace.</p>
            <p>But if we muſt have ſomething a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this abſurd Doctrine, let it be this; That every Perſon who is tolerated ſhall declare that no one ought to be puniſhed for holding either ſide of the queſtion. And I verily believe if the Papiſts were ſecure of enjoying the freedom of their Religion here, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming only ſuch Doctrines as are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with the Government, they would not be ſo violently bent to King <hi>James</hi>'s Intereſt, as to hazard the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ruine of themſelves and Families for his ſake.</p>
            <p>I pray God to encline our Minds to mild and moderate Councils. For as the Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter</hi> ſays in the concluſion of his ſecond Letter to the Lord <hi>Dorſet,</hi> — <hi>To calm Mens Minds for the future, to ſettle Affairs in a ſecure and laſting Peace, moſt certainly a gentle, generous, charitable Temper is the best.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
